<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="security-introduction">
  <title>Security - Introduction</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <para>
      The Seam Security module provides a number of useful features for securing your Java EE application, which are briefly
      summarised in the following sections.  The rest of the chapters contained in this documentation each focus on one
      major aspect of each of the following features.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Authentication</title>
      
      <para>
        <emphasis>Authentication</emphasis> is the act of establishing, or confirming, the identity of a user.  In many 
        applications a user confirms their identity by providing a username and password (also known as their 
        <emphasis>credentials</emphasis>). Seam Security allows the developer to control how users are authenticated, by 
        providing a flexible <emphasis>Authentication API</emphasis> that can be easily configured to allow authentication 
        against any number of sources, including but not limited to databases, LDAP directory servers or some other external 
        authentication service.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        If none of the built-in authentication providers are suitable for your application, then it is also possible to write
        your own custom Authenticator implementation.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Identity Management</title>
      
      <para>
        Identity Management is a set of useful APIs for managing the users, groups and roles within your application.  The
        identity management features in Seam are provided by PicketLink IDM, and allow you to manage users stored in a 
        variety of backend security stores, such as in a database or LDAP directory.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>External Authentication</title>

      <para>
        Seam Security contains an external authentication sub-module that provides a number of features for authenticating
        your application users against external authentication services, such as OpenID and SAML.
      </para>    
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Authorization</title>
      
      <para>
        While <emphasis>authentication</emphasis> is used to confirm the identity of the user, <emphasis>authorization</emphasis>
        is used to control which actions a user may perform within your application.  Authorization can be roughly divided
        into two categories; coarse-grained and fine-grained.  An example of a coarse-grained restriction is allowing only members of
        a certain group or role to perform a privileged operation.  A fine-grained restriction on the other hand may allow only
        a certain individual user to perform a specific action on a specific object within your application.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        There are also rule-based permissions, which bridge the gap between fine-grained and coarse-grained restrictions.  These
        permissions may be used to determine a user's privileges based on certain business logic.
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    
    <section>
      <title>Maven Dependencies</title>
      
      <para>
        The Maven artifacts for all Seam modules are hosted within the JBoss Maven repository.  Please refer to the
        <ulink url="http://community.jboss.org/wiki/MavenGettingStarted-Users">Maven Getting Started Guide</ulink> 
        for information about configuring your Maven installation to use the JBoss repository.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To use Seam Security within your Maven-based project, it is advised that you import the Seam BOM (Bill of
        Materials) which declares the versions for all Seam modules.  First declare a property value for
        <literal>${seam.version}</literal> as follows:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<properties>
  <seam.version>3.1.0.Final</seam.version>
</properties>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        You can check the <ulink url="https://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/org/jboss/seam/seam-bom/">JBoss Maven Repository</ulink> 
        directly to determine the latest version of the Seam BOM to use.
      </para>
        
      <para>
        Now add the following lines to the list of dependencies within the <literal>dependencyManagement</literal> 
        section of your project's <literal>pom.xml</literal> file:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-bom</artifactId>
  <version>${seam.version}</version>
  <type>pom</type>
  <scope>import</scope>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        Once that is done, add the following dependency (no version is required as it comes from <literal>seam-bom</literal>):
      </para>
              
      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.security</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-security</artifactId>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        If you wish to use the external authentication module in your application to allow authentication using OpenID or
        SAML, then add the following dependency also:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.security</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-security-external</artifactId>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>   
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Enabling the Security Interceptor</title>
      
      <para>
        To enable many of the features of Seam Security, the Security interceptor must be configured in your
        application's <literal>beans.xml</literal> file.  Add the following configuration to your 
        <literal>beans.xml</literal> to enable the Security Interceptor:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[    <interceptors>
        <class>org.jboss.seam.security.SecurityInterceptor</class>
    </interceptors>]]></programlisting>
    </section>
    
  </section>
    
</chapter>
