<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="security-authentication-external">
  <title>Security - External Authentication</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>
      The external authentication module is an optional add-on to the core Seam Security module, which provides a number of 
      features that enable your application to authenticate against third party identity services, via a number of supported protocols.
    </para>
    
    <warning>
      <para>
        The features described in this chapter are a <emphasis>preview</emphasis> only.  The APIs described may change
        in a subsequent version of Seam, and may not be backwards-compatible with previous versions.
      </para>
    </warning>
    
    <para>
      Currently this module supports authentication via OpenID, and other protocols (such as SAML and OAuth) are currently under 
      development for the next version of Seam.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Configuration</title>
      
      <para>
        If your project is Maven-based, then add the following dependency to your project:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.jboss.seam.security</groupId>
  <artifactId>seam-security-external</artifactId>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        If you are not using Maven, you must add the <literal>seam-security-external.jar</literal> library to your project, which
        can be found in the Seam Security downloadable distribution.
      </para>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>OpenID</title>
    
    <para>
      OpenID allows the users of your application to authenticate without requiring them to create an account.  When using OpenID, your user
      is temporarily redirected to the web site of their OpenID provider so that they can enter their password, after which they are redirected
      back to your application.  The OpenID authentication process is safe - at no time is the user's password seen by any site besides their
      OpenID provider.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      
      <para>
        The external authentication module provides support for OpenID based on <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/openid4java/">OpenID4Java</ulink>,
        an open source OpenID library (licensed under the Apache v2 license) with both Relying Party and Identity Provider capabilities.  This feature
        allows your application to authenticate its users against an external OpenID provider, such as Google or Yahoo, or to turn your application
        into an OpenID provider itself.
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <para>
          To see the OpenID features in action, take a look at the <literal>openid-rp</literal> example included in the Seam Security distribution.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Enabling OpenID for your application</title>
      
      <para>
        To use OpenID in your own application, you must configure Seam Security to use <code>OpenIdAuthenticator</code>, an 
        <code>Authenticator</code> implementation that performs authentication against an OpenID provider.  This authenticator
        is a named, session-scoped bean, with the following declaration:      
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @Named("openIdAuthenticator") @SessionScoped class OpenIdAuthenticator]]></programlisting>
      
      <section>
        <title>Using OpenID as your only authentication method</title>
        
        <para>
          If your application only uses OpenID to provide authentication services, then it is recommended 
          that <code>OpenIdAuthenticator</code> is selected by configuring the <code>authenticatorClass</code>
          property of the <code>Identity</code> bean.  The following code sample demonstrates how this might 
          be done by using Solder:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xmlns:s="urn:java:ee" 
   xmlns:security="urn:java:org.jboss.seam.security"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee http://jboss.org/schema/cdi/beans_1_0.xsd">

   <security:Identity>
      <s:modifies/>
      <security:authenticatorClass>org.jboss.seam.security.external.openid.OpenIdAuthenticator</security:authenticatorClass>
   </security:Identity>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Using OpenID as one of many possible authentication methods</title>
        
        <para>
          If your application gives the user a choice of which authentication method to use, then it is not possible to
          pre-configure which <code>Authenticator</code> implementation is used to authenticate.  In these circumstances,
          it is recommended that you configure the authenticator by specifying a value for the <code>authenticatorName</code> 
          property of the <code>Identity</code> bean.  This can be done by binding a view-layer control such as a radio group
          directly to this property, to allow the user to select the method of authentication they wish to use.  See the 
          following JSF code as an example:
        </para>        
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<h:outputLabel value="Authenticate using:"/>
<h:selectOneRadio id="authenticator" value="#{identity.authenticatorName}">
  <f:selectItem itemLabel="OpenID" itemValue="openIdAuthenticator" />
  <f:selectItem itemLabel="Custom" itemValue="customAuthenticator" />
</h:selectOneRadio>]]></programlisting>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Choosing which OpenID provider to use</title>
      
      <para>
        Seam provides built-in support for a number of well-known OpenID providers.  The <code>OpenIdAuthenticator</code> bean
        may be configured to select which OpenID provider will be used to process an authentication request.  Each concrete
        provider implements the following interface:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface OpenIdProvider {
   String getCode();
   String getName();
   String getUrl();
}]]></programlisting>
        
      <para>        
        The following table lists the providers that come pre-packaged in Seam:      
      </para>
      
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Provider</entry>
              <entry>Code</entry>
              <entry>Name</entry>
              <entry>URL</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>CustomOpenIdProvider</entry>
              <entry>custom</entry>
              <entry>Google</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>          
            <row>
              <entry>GoogleOpenIdProvider</entry>
              <entry>google</entry>
              <entry>Google</entry>
              <entry>https://www.google.com/accounts/o8/id</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>MyOpenIdProvider</entry>
              <entry>myopenid</entry>
              <entry>MyOpenID</entry>
              <entry>https://myopenid.com</entry>
            </row>     
            <row>
              <entry>YahooOpenIdProvider</entry>
              <entry>yahoo</entry>
              <entry>Yahoo</entry>
              <entry>https://me.yahoo.com</entry>
            </row>        
          </tbody>        
        </tgroup>      
      </informaltable>
      
      <para>
        To select one of the built-in providers to use for an authentication request, the <code>providerCode</code> property
        of the <code>OpenIdAuthenticator</code> bean should be set to one of the Code values from the above table.  The
        <code>OpenIdAuthenticator</code> bean provides a convenience method called <code>getProviders()</code> that returns
        a list of all known providers.  This may be used in conjunction with a radio group to allow the user to select which
        OpenID provider they wish to authenticate with - see the following JSF snippet for an example:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<h:selectOneRadio value="#{openIdAuthenticator.providerCode}">
  <f:selectItems value="#{openIdAuthenticator.providers}" var="p" itemValue="#{p.code}" itemLabel="#{p.name}"/>
</h:selectOneRadio>]]></programlisting>

      <section>
        <title>Using a custom OpenID provider</title>
        
        <para>
          If you would like to allow your users to specify an OpenID provider that is not supported out of the box by Seam, then
          the <code>CustomOpenIdProvider</code> may be used.  As it is a <code>@Named</code> bean, it can be accessed directly
          from the view layer via EL.  The following JSF code shows how you might allow the user to specify their own
          OpenID provider:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<h:outputLabel value="If you have selected the Custom OpenID provider, please provide a URL:"/>
<h:inputText value="#{customOpenIdProvider.url}"/>]]></programlisting>
      
      </section>
      
    
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Managing the OpenID authentication process</title>
      
      <para>
        Your application must provide an implementation of the <code>OpenIdRelyingPartySpi</code> interface to process 
        OpenID callback events.  This interface declares the following methods:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface OpenIdRelyingPartySpi {
   void loginSucceeded(OpenIdPrincipal principal, ResponseHolder responseHolder);
   void loginFailed(String message, ResponseHolder responseHolder);      
      ]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
        The implementation is responsible for processing the response of the OpenID authentication, and is typically used to
        redirect the user to an appropriate page depending on whether authentication was successful or not.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        There are two API calls that <emphasis>must</emphasis> be made in the case of a successful authentication.  The first one
        should notify the <code>OpenIdAuthenticator</code> that the authentication attempt was successful, and pass it the 
        <code>OpenIdPrincipal</code> object:
      </para>
      
      <warning>
        <para>
          If the following two API calls are omitted, unpredictable results may occur!
        </para>
      </warning>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[openIdAuthenticator.success(principal);]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
        Secondly, a <code>DeferredAuthenticationEvent</code> must be fired to signify that a deferred authentication attempt has
        been completed:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[deferredAuthentication.fire(new DeferredAuthenticationEvent());]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
        After making these two API calls, the implementation may perform whatever additional logic is required.  The following code
        shows a complete example:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[import java.io.IOException;

import javax.enterprise.event.Event;
import javax.inject.Inject;
import javax.servlet.ServletContext;

import org.jboss.seam.security.events.DeferredAuthenticationEvent;
import org.jboss.seam.security.external.api.ResponseHolder;
import org.jboss.seam.security.external.openid.OpenIdAuthenticator;
import org.jboss.seam.security.external.openid.api.OpenIdPrincipal;
import org.jboss.seam.security.external.spi.OpenIdRelyingPartySpi;

public class OpenIdRelyingPartySpiImpl implements OpenIdRelyingPartySpi {
   @Inject private ServletContext servletContext;
   @Inject OpenIdAuthenticator openIdAuthenticator;   
   @Inject Event<DeferredAuthenticationEvent> deferredAuthentication;

   public void loginSucceeded(OpenIdPrincipal principal, ResponseHolder responseHolder) {
      try {
         openIdAuthenticator.success(principal);
         deferredAuthentication.fire(new DeferredAuthenticationEvent());
         
         responseHolder.getResponse().sendRedirect(servletContext.getContextPath() + "/UserInfo.jsf");
      } catch (IOException e) {
         throw new RuntimeException(e);
      }
   }

   public void loginFailed(String message, ResponseHolder responseHolder) {
      try {
         responseHolder.getResponse().sendRedirect(servletContext.getContextPath() + "/AuthenticationFailed.jsf");
      } catch (IOException e) {
         throw new RuntimeException(e);
      }
   }
}]]></programlisting>
   
    </section>  
  
  </section>
  
  
    
</chapter>
