<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="security-authentication">
  <title>Security - Authentication</title>

  <section>
    <title>Basic Concepts</title>
       
    <para>
      The majority of the Security API is centered around the <literal>Identity</literal> bean.  This bean represents the
      identity of the current user, the default implementation of which is a session-scoped, named bean.  This
      means that once logged in, a user's identity is scoped to the lifecycle of their current session.  The two most
      important methods that you need to know about at this stage in regard to authentication are <literal>login()</literal> and
      <literal>logout()</literal>, which as the names suggest are used to log the user in and out, respectively.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      As the default implementation of the <literal>Identity</literal> bean is named, it may be referenced via an EL
      expression, or be used as the target of an EL action.  Take the following JSF code snippet for example:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[  <h:commandButton action="#{identity.login}" value="Log in"/>    
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      This JSF command button would typically be used in a login form (which would also contain inputs for the user's username
      and password) that allows the user to log into the application.
    </para>
    
    <note>
      <para>
        The bean type of the <literal>Identity</literal> bean is <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.Identity</literal>.  This
        interface is what you should inject if you need to access the <literal>Identity</literal> bean from your
        own beans.  The default implementation is <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.IdentityImpl</literal>.
      </para>
    </note>
    
    <para>
      The other important bean to know about right now is the <literal>Credentials</literal> bean.  Its' purpose is to
      hold the user's credentials (such as their username and password) before the user logs in.  The default implementation
      of the <literal>Credentials</literal> bean is also a session-scoped, named bean (just like the <literal>Identity</literal>
      bean).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <literal>Credentials</literal> bean has two properties, <literal>username</literal> and <literal>credential</literal>
      that are used to hold the current user's username and credential (e.g. a password) values.  The default implementation of
      the <literal>Credentials</literal> bean provides an additional convenience property called <literal>password</literal>,
      which may be used in lieu of the <literal>credential</literal> property when a simple password is required.
    </para>
    
    <note>
      <para>
        The bean type of the <literal>Credential</literal> bean is <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.Credentials</literal>.  The
        default implementation for this bean type is <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.CredentialsImpl</literal>.
        Also, as credentials may come in many forms (such as passwords, biometric data such as that from a fingerprint reader, etc) the
        <literal>credential</literal> property of the <literal>Credentials</literal> bean must be able to support each variation,
        not just passwords.  To allow for this, any credential that implements the <literal>org.picketlink.idm.api.Credential</literal>
        interface is a valid value for the <literal>credential</literal> property.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Built-in Authenticators</title>
    
    <para>
      The Seam Security module provides the following built-in <literal>Authenticator</literal> implementations:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.jaas.JaasAuthenticator</literal> - used to authenticate against a JAAS
          configuration defined by the container.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.management.IdmAuthenticator</literal> - used to authenticate against an
          Identity Store using the Identity Management API.  See the Identity Management chapter for details on how
          to configure this authenticator.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.external.openid.OpenIdAuthenticator</literal> (provided by the external module) - used 
          to authenticate against an external OpenID provider, such as Google, Yahoo, etc.  See the External Authentication chapter
          for details on how to configure this authenticator.
        </para>
      </listitem>      
      
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Which Authenticator will Seam use?</title>
  
    <para>
      The <literal>Identity</literal> bean has an <literal>authenticatorClass</literal> property, which if set will be used
      to determine which <literal>Authenticator</literal> bean implementation to invoke during the
      authentication process.  This property may be set by configuring it with a predefined authenticator type,
      for example by using Solder XML Config.  The following XML configuration example shows how you would configure the
      <literal>Identity</literal> bean to use the <literal>com.acme.MyCustomerAuthenticator</literal> bean for authentication:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<beans xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xmlns:s="urn:java:ee" 
   xmlns:security="urn:java:org.jboss.seam.security"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee http://jboss.org/schema/cdi/beans_1_0.xsd">
       
   <security:IdentityImpl>
      <s:modifies/>      
      <security:authenticatorClass>com.acme.MyCustomAuthenticator</security:authenticatorClass>
   </security:IdentityImpl>      
</beans>]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      Alternatively, if you wish to be able to select the <literal>Authenticator</literal> to authenticate with by
      specifying the name of the <literal>Authenticator</literal> implementation (i.e. for those annotated with
      the <literal>@Named</literal> annotation), the <literal>authenticatorName</literal> property may be set instead.  
      This might be useful if you wish to offer your users the choice of how they would like to authenticate, whether it
      be through a local user database, an external OpenID provider, or some other method.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The following example shows how you might configure the <literal>authenticatorName</literal> property with the
      Seam Config module:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<beans xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xmlns:s="urn:java:ee" 
   xmlns:security="urn:java:org.jboss.seam.security"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee http://jboss.org/schema/cdi/beans_1_0.xsd">
   <security:IdentityImpl>
      <s:modifies/>
      <security:authenticatorName>openIdAuthenticator</security:authenticatorName>
   </security:IdentityImpl>      
</beans>]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      If neither the <literal>authenticatorClass</literal> or <literal>authenticatorName</literal> properties are set,
      then the authentication process with automatically use a custom <literal>Authenticator</literal> implementation, if
      the developer has provided one (and only one) within their application.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If neither property is set, and the user has not provided a custom <literal>Authenticator</literal>, then the
      authentication process will fall back to the Identity Management API to attempt to authenticate the user.
    </para>

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Writing a custom Authenticator</title>
    
    <para>
      All <literal>Authenticator</literal> implementations must implement the <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.Authenticator</literal>
      interface. This interface defines the following methods:
    </para> 
      
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface Authenticator {
  void authenticate();   
  void postAuthenticate();   
  User getUser();   
  AuthenticationStatus getStatus();
}]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      The <literal>authenticate()</literal> method is invoked during the authentication process and is responsible for performing the
      work necessary to validate whether the current user is who they claim to be.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <literal>postAuthenticate()</literal> method is invoked after the authentication process has already completed, and
      may be used to perform any post-authentication business logic, such as setting session variables, logging, auditing, etc.    
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <literal>getUser()</literal> method should return an instance of <literal>org.picketlink.idm.api.User</literal>, 
      which is generally determined during the authentication process.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The <literal>getStatus()</literal> method must return the current status of authentication, represented by the
      <literal>AuthenticationStatus</literal> enum.  Possible values are <literal>SUCCESS</literal>, <literal>FAILURE</literal>
      and <literal>DEFERRED</literal>.  The <literal>DEFERRED</literal> value should be used for special circumstances, such as
      asynchronous authentication as a result of authenticating against a third party as is the case with OpenID, etc.
    </para>
      
    <para>
      The easiest way to get started writing your own custom authenticator is to extend the 
      <literal>org.jboss.seam.security.BaseAuthenticator</literal> abstract class.  This class implements the 
      <literal>getUser()</literal> and <literal>getStatus()</literal> methods for you, and provides 
      <literal>setUser()</literal> and <literal>setStatus()</literal> methods for setting both the user and status values.
    </para>
    
    <warning>
      <para>
        An <literal>Authenticator</literal> implementation cannot be a stateless session bean.
      </para>
    </warning>    
    
    <para>
      To access the user's credentials from within the <literal>authenticate()</literal> method, you can inject the
      <literal>Credentials</literal> bean like so:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject Credentials credentials;]]></programlisting>
    
    <para>
      Once the credentials are injected, the <literal>authenticate()</literal> method is responsible for checking that
      the provided credentials are valid.  Here is a complete example:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class SimpleAuthenticator extends BaseAuthenticator implements Authenticator {
   @Inject Credentials credentials;
   
   @Override
   public void authenticate() {
      if ("demo".equals(credentials.getUsername()) && 
            credentials.getCredential() instanceof PasswordCredential &&
            "demo".equals(((PasswordCredential) credentials.getCredential()).getValue()))  {
         setStatus(AuthenticationStatus.SUCCESS);
         setUser(new SimpleUser("demo"));
      }
   }
}]]></programlisting>

   <note>
     <para>
       The above code was taken from the simple authentication example, included in the Seam Security distribution.
     </para>
   </note>
   
   <para>
     In the above code, the <literal>authenticate()</literal> method checks that the user has provided a username of
     <emphasis>demo</emphasis> and a password of <emphasis>demo</emphasis>.  If so, the authentication is deemed as successful
     and the status is set to <literal>AuthenticationStatus.SUCCESS</literal>, and a new <literal>SimpleUser</literal> instance 
     is created to represent the authenticated user.  
   </para>
   
   <warning>
     <para>
       The <literal>Authenticator</literal> implementation <emphasis>must</emphasis> return a non-null value when 
       <literal>getUser()</literal> is invoked if authentication is successful.  Failure to return a non-null value
       will result in an <literal>AuthenticationException</literal> being thrown.
     </para>
   </warning>
  
  </section>
    
</chapter>
